Coming back to local filters, there's another extremely important and extremely
欢迎回到局部滤波部分 我们要介绍另一个非常重要
appropriate local filter which is called a median filter,
并且用途广泛的局部滤波器 那就是中值滤波器
which we are going to describe next. And it's a great filter because it
接下来我们将对其进行详细的讲解 这是一种很棒的滤波器
doesn't really blur edges. And although it's a very classical
因为它不会使边缘变得模糊不清 而且尽管它是一种很经典的滤波器
filter, it's still very useful today. So, let's observe it.
但是在今天仍然很常用 那下面就开始中值滤波的学习
Before we actually describe it, let's see what happens with a real image.
在正式讲解中值滤波器之前 先来看一个实物图像的例子
We have here an image, that has been contaminated with what's called salt and
这里有一幅被椒盐噪声污染的图像
pepper noise. Next week, we're actually going to
下周 我们会为大家
describe different models of noise a bit better, but salt and pepper, it's just
进一步讲解不同的噪声模型 这个椒盐噪声
noise that basically is very strong noise, individually added at different
是一种比较剧烈的噪声 分别加在各个像素上
pixels. We see it here.
请看这里
This is the result of the local mean filter.
这是局部均值滤波的结果
What we have seen in the previous videos, just local averaging,
是在此前的视频中看到过的
in this case, a three by three. You might be able to observe there is
就是一个 3×3 的局部平均 可以观察到
some reduction of noise but not really too much reduction of noise.
是有一些噪声的减少 但并不是很多
Here, on the other hand, is the result of a three by three median filter and we see
再看这里 是 3×3 中值滤波的结果
a great result. We don't see blurring.
可以观察到一个很好的效果 并没有出现模糊
we actually see that a lot of the noise has been reduced.
可以观察到大多数的噪声的确都被滤掉了
We could reduce much more noise with a local mean filter, a local average.
我们可以通过一个比 3×3 大的局部均值滤波器
If we go beyond three by three, we might go five by five, nine by nine.
来过滤掉更多的噪声 像 5×5 或者 9×9
Remember, by averaging we are reducing the noise by square of the number of
就像在之前的视频中提到过的 在均值滤波的过程中
pixels that we are averaging as we saw in the previous videos.
我们对平方个个数的像素值进行了平均
But if we enlarge the neighborhood, we also saw that we are going to start to
但是 如果增大滤波时的邻域 可以发现
blur a lot of the details. On the other hand,
有很多细节都被模糊了 而另一方面
keeping a three by three neighborhood would still get extremely good denoising
用一个 3×3 邻域的中值滤波器依然能够达到很好的去噪效果
with the median filter. So, what's the median filter?
那么什么是中值滤波器呢？
Very simple. What we do, is we actually take, let's
很简单 就是这样
say, if we are working in a three by three neighborhood,
如果选取一个 3×3 的领域
we basically order the pixels so we basically order them from the smallest to
将这个模板里的所有像素按照从小到大的顺序排列
the largest and we pick the one in the middle,
然后选取最中间的那个
okay? So, we start putting all the pixels in
明白了吗？就是将所有的像素排序
order, we pick the one in the middle. This is an operation we actually learn in
然后提取出最中间的那个 这个运算是大家小学就学过的吧
elementary school. And it's an extremely powerful, replace
这个功能相当强大
it by the one in the middle. So, for example, if you have pixels which
用排在最中间的那个值代替了待处理的像素点 举个例子
look like this and one of the pixels is very noisy,
如果这儿有一些这样的像素点 其中的一个有很高的噪声
when you order them, this one is going to be replaced by one
当排序的时候 这个点就会被这些等值的点的值替换
of these values that are all equal so it's going to be replaced, it's going to
也就是说 这个像素点的值会被替换掉
go down, okay?
这个值就会变小
So, the noise is clean. Completely clean, without blurring as we
就这样 噪声就被清除掉了 非常的干净
have seen for Gaussian filtering or for mean filtering.
没有出现之前在高斯滤波或者均值滤波中的模糊的效果
It's a very, very simple filter. You order, and you pick the one in the
均值滤波器是一种非常简单的滤波器 只需排序 然后挑选出最中间的元素
middle. You order from the smallest to the
按从小到大排序
largest, and you pick the one in the middle.
然后挑选出排在最中间的那个
And then, you move to the next window. So, you basically take a three by three
然后移到下一个窗口 所以就只需每次处理一个 3×3 的窗口
window, then you move to the next window, the next window, the next window.
然后移到下一个窗口处理 再下一个窗口 再下一个
And you get this extremely simple filter, the median filter.
这样 大家就掌握了这个非常简单的 中值滤波器
Before I show you additional examples of the median filter in real time, we're
在我使用 MATLAB 来给大家实时演示
going to actual run MatLab to do that. Let me just give you one interesting
中值滤波器的实例之前 先来看一下
property of the median filter. We saw in a couple of views ago that the
中值滤波器的一个很有趣的性质 在之前的视频中
average filter is reducing this, a minus ai squared. We say the average is the
已经了解到 均值滤波器按 (a-ai)^2 的方式来减少噪声
value of a that reduces, that minimizes this and I'm summing over all the pixels.
这里均值就是这个a 它使得这个式子取最小值 将所有的像素点都加起来
So, I'm going to ask you a question, can we represent the median filtering in a
现在 我要问大家一个问题 我们可不可以把中值滤波器也写成这样的形式呢？
form like this? A different function maybe.
也许是另外一个函数
Some of certain function of a minus ai, can we do that?
就像这样 f(a-ai) 可以写成这样的函数吗？
Just think for a while, and tell me yes or no, if you know the answer of that.
思考一下 如果想到了答案 告诉我可不可以
So, what's the answer to this question? Very interesting.
那么 答案是什么呢？很有趣
This is the mean. The value of a that minimizes the square
这是均值 使这个平方误差取得最小值的 a 就是均值
error is the mean. What's the median?
那什么是中值呢？
The median is the value that minimizes the absolute.
中值可以使得 (a-ai) 的绝对值取得最小值
There's no square here. It's just the absolute difference.
这里没有平方 而是差值的绝对值
It's extremely interesting that by replacing this square by basically
非常有趣的是 仅仅是将这个平方符号
nothing, just absolute value, we get the median.
换成绝对值 就得到了中值
Once again, you can prove this. It's a bit more of a difficult proof,
依旧 大家可以自己证明一下 可能会有一点困难
because when we discuss how to prove this, we say, just take derivatives, make
因为当讨论怎样证明均值的时候 会对这个式子求导
the derivative equal to zero, and you're going to find that a is the average of
使导数等于0 可以发现 a 就是所有 ai 的均值
all the ai's. Here, you're not allowed to take
但是在这里不能求导
derivative, because at zero, the absolute value cannot have a, doesn't have a
因为在0点 绝对值不存在导数
derivative. So, the proof is a bit more delicate.
所以 这个证明会用到更多技巧
But I'm sure that you can do it as a bonus exercise.
但是我相信大家可以做到 这个作为大家额外的奖励作业
Don't worry too much about that for now. You can believe me, that if you don't
大家不用考虑太多 如果不想自己证明
want to do the proof by yourself, that the result of minimizing this is the
可以先相信我的结论 使得这个式子最小的
median filter. An extremely interesting operation.
就是中值滤波器 一个特别有趣的运算
For those that are familiar with the area of robot statistics,
对于熟悉稳健统计这个领域的人而言
this is a square error, which is not very robust, and that's why it's blurring.
这个是平方误差 鲁棒性并不太强 所以均值滤波会有模糊
This is a much more robust error. And that's why it's able to completely
而相比之下这个误差鲁棒性比刚才的强 这也是中值滤波能够完全消除
eliminate noise, like salt and pepper noise, without blurring the rest of the
像椒盐噪声之类噪声的原因 而不使图像其它部分模糊
image. The last interesting property I want to
我想提到的 最后一个关于中值的有趣性质就是
mention about the median is in the average, the result doesn't have to be
在均值中 得到的结果并不是模板中的某个像素值
one of the pixels. So, for example, if you're averaging one
举个例子 如果算 1 和 2 的均值
and two, you get 1.5. It's not one, it's not two,
得到的是1.5 而既不是1 也不是2
okay? When you're averaging, let's say, a three
当计算均值的时候 比如一个 3×3 的模板
by, when you're completing the average of a
当计算完这个 3×3 的均值后
three by three and you're replacing the middle pixel by the average, you might be
用均值代替了中间的那个像素
replacing the pixel by a value that doesn't show up,
也许就用一个根本没有出现过的值代替了这个像素
not in the three by three window, maybe not even in the whole image.
这个值可能没有在这个 3×3 的窗口中出现过 甚至可能在整个图像中也都没出现过
Once again, the average between, of one and two is 1.5,
再说一遍 1和2的均值是1.5
a new value. On the other hand, when you're doing the
是一个新值 从这个角度而言 当进行中值滤波的时候
median filtering, you're always replacing by one of the values that already exist
总是用一个在 3×3 的窗口中存在的值来进行替换
in the three by three window. So, you're not producing new pixel
也就是说 并没有弄出一个新的像素值出来
values. And that's part of what's happening here.
而这是其中的部分过程
And that's a very interesting property by itself.
这个性质确实十分有趣
There is no novelty. There is no new values.
用的是已有值 没有新值出现
Only those that are already familiar in the neighborhood of the pixel that you
只是这个像素点周围邻域像素点的中值
are replacing the pixel with the median. Now,
被选择来替代它的值
now, that we know about the median, now that we know some of the interesting
既然已经学习了中值 以及它的一些有趣的性质
properties of the median, let's just see a few additional examples
接下来 就来看一些关于中值滤波器的操作实例
of the median filter in action. Let's see that in the next video.
下一个视频再见
Thank you.
谢谢大家